Guide to the Ezra C. Stiles Collection, 1916-1953 AIS.2000.08
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Ezra C. Stiles Collection
1916-1953
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Stiles, Ezra C.
AIS.2000.08
34 oversized_folders
Ezra C. Stiles was one of western Pennsylvania's top landscape architects, designing gardens for several of Pittsburgh's prominent families, including the Scaifes, Corsons, Frownes, and Garmens. He also consulted for the Carnegie Steel Works and participated in a number of public works projects, drafting plans for parks, cemeteries, and schools. The collection consists entirely of blueprints originating from Stiles' office, relating to various projects commissioned by private citizens, corporations, and city governments. The blueprints were found arranged in a collage-like manner pasted to the walls and ceiling in the attic office of Stiles' former house, often with two or three works overlapping one another. Spanning the years 1916 through 1953, this collection represents the only consolidated grouping of Stiles' work.
Biography
Born in Painted Post, New York, in 1891, Ezra C. Stiles moved to southwestern Pennsylvania as a young child. After completing his studies at Penn State University, Stiles served in the Army Corp of Engineers in Europe during the First World War. During his military service, Stiles toured gardens in France and Luxembourg, an experience that would influence the course of his career in the following decades. Upon returning home, Stiles found work with the A.W. Smith Company, a landscaping and floral business, and in 1926 he established his own landscape architecture business based out of the Renshaw Building in downtown Pittsburgh.
As his career progressed, Stiles became an increasingly prolific architect. He completed projects for individuals, corporations, and city planners. Stiles designed gardens for many prominent Pittsburgh families, including the Scaifes, Corsons, Frownes, and Garmens. He also consulted on a number of construction projects for the Carnegie Steel Works, the Rockwell Manufacturing Corporation, and the Robertshaw Fulton Company.
Stiles' most enduring work is in the public sphere, examples of which include garden designs for Clarion City Park, Altoona's Alto-Reste Cemetery, and Furman University in Greenville, South Carolina. From the late 1950s through the 1960s, Stiles' firm created designed two city parks for the Pittsburgh bicentennial.
Although Stiles is known as one of the area's top landscape architects, he also worked as an urban planner, writer, mapmaker, and painter.
Scope and Content Notes
The collection consists entirely of blueprints originating from Stiles' office, relating to various projects commissioned by private citizens, corporations, and city governments. Spanning the years 1916 through 1953, this collection represents the only consolidated grouping of Stiles' hand-rendered engineering blueprints. The blueprints were discovered arranged in a collage-like manner applied to the walls and ceiling in the attic office of Stiles' former house in Oakmont (13 miles northeast of Pittsburgh) with a water-soluble adhesive. The prints, which in some cases were pasted over sections of one another, vary in quality and state of deterioration. A number of the blueprints suffer from discoloration caused by the wallpaper upon which they had been pasted. Given the diversity of these materials, the collection is arranged in four series.
The first series in the collection consists of Stiles' landscape architecture work, dating from 1918 through the 1940s. While most of the designs are for families in the Pittsburgh area, there are several projects done for clients outside the region. These documents reveal how Stiles used western Pennsylvania's uneven terrain to his benefit by creating flowered terraces or waterfalls amid the landscape. Researchers will also note Stiles' use of perennials and the strategic central placement of sundials and ponds.
The second series contains some of Stiles' public works. Here, venues such as cemeteries, public parks, and schools are presented. Although Stiles was instrumental in his work for the Pittsburgh Regional Parks system, this collection does not include such material. Still, his designs for the Clarion City Park and Schenley Park (both in the Pittsburgh area) represent a similar effort. The design for the Alto-Reste Cemetery in Altoona remains one of the best preserved documents in the collection. The records also reveal that Stiles' work was in demand as far south as Greenville, South Carolina, where he did landscape architecture work for Furman University.
The third series consists of engineering blueprints found hanging on the walls of Stiles' office, the bulk of which date from the 1940s. Unlike the works found elsewhere in the collection, these documents were created for industrial and public works projects. Although Stiles did not create all of the prints, notes on some of the records indicate that he studied the prints and consulted on the projects. The prints mostly pertain to efforts undertaken by the Carnegie Steel Corporation at their plants in Duquesne and Munhall, Pennsylvania. Also represented are public works designs, including a 1941 project that widened and added intersections to McKnight Road.
When these materials were gathered from Stiles' office, a number of the very brittle prints fell apart. The final series houses fragments which could not be confidently identified with the project to which it belongs.
Details relating to the client, property and design were taken directly from the drawing and are listed in the item-level scope and content section. When available, additional information is noted in a supplemental paragraph.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Previous Citation
Ezra C. Stiles Collection, 1916-1953, AIS.2000.08, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Existence and Location of Originals
Folder 11 is located with oversized material.
Environment; Architecture; Blueprints (Reprographic copies); Allegheny County (Pa.); Engineering drawings -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County.; Landscape architectural projects -- United States; Landscape architectural projects -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; Pittsburgh (Pa.); Business and Industry; Landscape architectural drawing -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; Landscape architects -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; Stiles, Ezra C.
- Ezra C. Stiles, Landscape Architecture, 1916-1948; I.
  - Thomas Well Jr., Esq. Estate, 1916-1923 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Youngstown, Ohio
    A.W. Smith Co., Landscape Dept., Keenan Building, Pittsburgh, PA
    Ralph F. Pinner, Landscape Architect
    Scale 1/8"=1'. Shows drainage, terraces. Drawing shows edge outline of footprint of house with formal, terraced, garden spaces of lily pool, rose garden, pergola stone steps. Drawing not intact. Torn at top, some lettering missing. Drawing has uneven cut on bottom (probably old), bottom and left side missing.
  - R.S. and --B. Mebane, June 1920 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 1)
    Great Falls, South Carolina
    E.S. Draper, Landscape Architect -- City Planner
    11 East --Street, Charlotte, N.C.
    Studied by ESD, ECS
    Drafted by ECS
    Checked by FG
    Approved by HHB
    Proposed Bath House For Plan # 1075-8. Front elevation of formal bath house with grey limestone or brown sandstone block niche. Plan of bathhouse illustrates interior layout and exterior entrance. Details for oak doors, details for ornamental beam, detail showing form of pool light. Standard size drawing, torn in spots with slight discoloration at edges. Wallpaper showing through at edge.
  - Estate of E.F. Clark, Esq., 1923 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 1)
    A.W. Smith Co. Landscape Dept.
    Keenan Building, Pittsburgh, PA
    EC Stiles, Landscape
    Elevation of garden and a list of planting material.
  - Estate of E.F. Clark, Esq., undated (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 1)
    Flower and pool garden.
  - F.M. Graff, 1923 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 1)
    Blairsville, PA
    Location plan for entrance drive
    Based on a preliminary survey by Albert Smith
  - Mr. A. S. Hanes, Esq., 1919 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 1)
    Winston – Salem – North Carolina
    E.S. Draper, Landscape Architect & City Planner
  - Estate of Mr. Henry Wall, undated (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 2)
    Rockingham, NC
    E.S. Draper, Landscape Architect
    506 Trust Building, Charlotte, NC
    Details of lattice and brickwork. Scale on each of details. Drawing contains section and elevation drawings of lattice fencing, sections of brick steps, plan of lattice hood for statue, elevation of hooded statue, house terrace showing plan of detail of brick paving, elevation of house terrace. Wallpaper showing through on drawing. Right border of drawing missing.
  - Estate of Mr. Henry Wall, c.a.-1919 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 2)
    Scale 1"=10'
    Plantings
  - Emslie Nicholson, October 1920 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 3)
    Union, SC
    E.S. Draper Landscape Architect And City Planner
    11 East 5th Street, Charlotte, NC
    Scale 1" = 16'
    Sheet no. 1 to accompany plan no. 1125-1. Perspective rendering of stone home with side and back view. Floor layouts of first and second floor.
  - G.B Ryland, Esq., October 1922 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 3)
    Beacon Street Schenley Park
    A.W. Smith Co., Landscape Dept., Keenan Buildingg, Pittsburgh, PA
    E. C. Stiles, Landscape Architect
    Studied by ECS
    Drawn by HR
    Checked by ECS
    Approved by EC Stiles
    Plan #1607-1
    Scale 1" – 10'
    "Preliminary General Plan For Portion of Property." Formal garden plan with curved pergola, stone paved walk linking centered garden spaces of circular sundial area, grass panels, and flower gardens. Drawing also includes a perspective of 'bird bath from porch,' and a 'Section of Garden Looking through Sundial.' Standard size drawing; has been damaged by the wallpaper in Stiles' office.
  - Edward Tomajko, April 1924 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 3)
    Adamsburg, PA
    A.W. Smith Co., Landscape Dept.
    E.C. Stiles, Landscape Architect
    Drafted by CVB
    Checked By ECS
    Plan # 1737-1
    General landscape plan. Large property with formal gardens close to residence, including sunken garden, enclosed lawn area, brick terrace. Cow stable, vegetable garden, clothes drying area near rear of property (near vehicle turn). Off Lincoln Highway.
  - For the Property of D. F. Ritter, September 1924 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 3)
    Indiana, Pennsylvania
    Scale 1" = 10', September 1924
    A.W. Smith Co. Landscape Dept. Pittsburgh
    Drafted by W. Cook and R.S.I
    Approved by E.C. Stiles
    Revised grades, drainage, water supply, lighting
    Plan # J752-3
    Grading & Utilities Plan. Formal garden with multiple levels, rectilinear and curvilinear garden rooms. Duplicate plan.
  - Estate of D. Ritter, Esq., November 21, 1924 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 3)
    Indiana –- Pennsylvania
    AW Smith Co. Landscape Dept., Pittsburgh, PA
    Scale ¼
    "Perennial Garden And Spring Bulbs in Rose Garden." Formal garden space of Perennial Garden with grass panel, bird houses with light, geometric layout with arched seating area. Key list of plant material. Iris arientatis, digitalis, saxifraga cordifolia, artemisia stalleriatia, pachysandra terminalis, iris sibirica, larksspur, catmint, stachys lanata. Formal rose garden layout in next section. Stone wall and possible brick wall outlining space with rose parterre beds outlined with newly placed tulips lining bed. In center or 4 parterred space is a sundial with grass panels separating all beds. Narcissus Empress outline border beds on outside edges of parterred space. Bulbs.. crocus, narcissus empress, tulip psyche, t. bartignen, painted lady, t. ouida. 1' Drawing mostly intact, just border torn off. Drawing is discolored and torn away in some places.
  - Edward --, ca. 1925 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 3)
    AW Smith Co., Landscape Dept., Pittsburgh, PA
    Lincoln Highway
    Elevation of garden and property with entrance at Lincoln Highway. Plant listing. Title of property and owner obscured by tear in page.
  - Mrs. W.H. McAfee, April 1928 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 4)
    6500 Beacon Street, Pittsburgh, PA
    A.W. Smith Co., Landscape Dept., Pittsburgh, PA
    Ezra Stiles
    Scales noted
    Plan No. 1836
    Wood fence with panel top detail. Plan of flower garden. Scale 1/8" = 1'-0". Conceptual plan showing octagonal pool surrounded by stone paving. The pool is centered in formal beds of flowers are connected by grass paths. Noted on drawing that fence to be painted an Italian green. Small drawing with water damage at edges. Slightly torn in places.
  - Mr. Roger W. Andrews, July 1929 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 4)
    Waldheim Road, Aspinwall PA
    Ezra C. Stiles, Landscape Architect, Pittsburgh, PA
    Drafted by E.R. (or F.R.)
    Scale 1/8"= 1'-0"
    Plan # 681-4
    Planting Plan for Flower Garden Area. Plan for two formal flower gardens, surrounded by brick walk with a shelter at one end and a pool feature anchoring the other end. Privet hedge separates the flower garden from other area. Combined list of plant material shown using a numeric key to identify plants. Some plants are viburnum opulus nana, heuchera sanguainea, santolina, digitalis, gailllardia grandifolia. Rock garden plants described as sedum sieboldi, veronica incana, alyssum saxitile, cerastium tomentosum, dianthus plumarius. Small drawing. Good condition, some slight discoloration, and tear.
  - Mr. Roger W. Andrews, Revised July 31, 1929 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 4)
    General planting plan for residence grounds.
    Plan # 581-3
    Plan in good condition, slight tear, some slight discoloration. Duplicate.
  - Mr. Roger W. Andrews, July 1929 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 4)
    Waldheim Road, Aspinwall, PA
    Ezra C. Stiles Landscape Architect
    706 Renshaw Building, Pittsburgh, PA
    Plan revised July 31, 1929
    Scale 1/16"= 1'0"
    Plan shows informal garden rooms, living lawn, croquet & archery lawn, entrance court, driving green surrounding the residence. A formal garden room, the flower garden, placed in center front of property. Rock garden, stone overlook with seat, garden house, grape arbor, shelter, place at endpoints. Plant list includes hyddrangea quercifolia, clethra alnifolia, viburnum motte, syringa vulgaris, cercis canadensis, betula alba, picaea alba, kalmia laifolia rhododendron maximum, monarda didyma (Oswego tea). Small size drawing.
  - Mr. Roger W. Andrews, Revised July 31, 1929 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 4)
  - Mr. L.P. Montgomery, July 1930 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 5)
    Mr. Lebanon, Twp, Allegheny, PA
    Ezra C. Stiles, Landscape Architect
    704 Renshaw Building, Pittsburgh
    Plan No. 1673-2
    Garden Arbor Shelter. Scales Noted. Elevation and floor plan showing roof plan of shelter. End elevation shown and details of posts and brackets. Formal design with cat cut-outs on bottom rail. Handwritten on back "extra blueprints to paste up." Standard size drawing, good condition. Slight water damage and discoloration.
  - Property of Mr. P.K. Rodgers, September 1930 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 5)
    South Negley Ave.
    Pittsburgh, PA
    Ezra C. Stiles, Landscape Architect, Renshaw Building, Pittsburgh
    Thomas Pringle, Registered Architect Pittsburgh, PA
    Plan no. 1690-1
    Scale 1/8" = 1'-0"
    "Grading & Plot Plan Showing House Location & Grade Lines." Plan shows old and new grades. Garden rooms noted, children's play yard, paved garden, flower garden, garage court. Standard drawing with slight water damage at bottom.
  - MR. P.K. Rodgers, September 1930 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 5)
    South Negley Ave., Pittsburgh, PA
    Ezra C. Stiles Landscape Architect, Renshaw Building, Pgh
    Thomas Pringle Regl. Architect, Pittsburgh, PA
    Plan # 16902
    Scale 1/8" = 1
    "General Landscape Plan for the Residence Property." Layout showing front screened lawn, hedges along side of property plan. Stone walk alongside to stone terrace and formal flower garden. Stone steps lead up to stone paved garden and then to children's play yard. Urban garden. Drawing possibly intact, cut along right border looks like part of drawing might be missing.
  - Property of J.C. Roush, January 1931 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 6)
    Conneat Lake, PA
    George D. Bowers, Landscape Architect
    713 Washington Avenue, Carnegie, PA
    Ezra C. Stiles, Consulting Landscape Architect, Pittsburgh, PA
    "Planting Plan Showing Layout of Rock Garden." Drawing shows rock garden layout and plant list. Plants include phlox sublata pink, arabis alpina, sedum sieboldi, veronica incana, santolina incana, vinca minor, wisteria.
  - Mr. J. M. Thorp, 1934 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 6)
    Maple Ave. Edgewood, PA
    704 Renshaw Building, Pittsburgh, PA
    Plan # 766-4
    Scale 1/8 = 1' – 0"
    Design for Wood Arbor Plan in garden. Small drawing 1x 1'2" of oak arbor.
  - Mr. & Mrs. Elias Sunstein, May 1935 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 6)
    5506 Aylesboro Avenue, Pittsburgh, PA
    704 Renshaw Building
    512 California Avenue, Oakmont, PA
    Scale 1" = 8' –0"
    "Preliminary Plan for the Residence Property." Small Drawing, 10.5" x 2'2". Rectilinear garden with front lawn skirted with bank planting and flower borders. Stone walk leads from porch to rectangular stone terrace.
  - Scott, Mr. & Mrs. Howard, 1937 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 7)
    Woodside Road, Forest Hills
    Plan # 1889-1
    1"=10'.
    Plan intact. Planting plan of residential garden shows contour lines, front lawn informal, side garnered informal lawn, right side stone stepping path, back formal spaces, and centered flower bed with center lawn panel which ends in wall with pool. Steps on each end of the wall lead to lower terraced gravel sitting room with table, bench and chairs. Other connected room is cooking space with pantry and fireplace, then vegetable garden area to play area and laundry area. Service court area with vegetable and orchard. Plant material contains buddleia variddii, berberis thunbergii, cornus alba siberica, forsythia intermedia, philadelphus coronaries (mock orange), syringe persica, syringe vulgaris, viburnum opulus, v. plicatum, populus nigra, fastigrata, salix babylonica, clematis paniculata (star clematis), bigonia radicans, wisteria sinensis, and phlox divaricata.
  - Mr. & Mrs. F. A. Evans, April 1937 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 7)
    5300 Wilkins Ave, Pittsburgh, PA
    Scale 1/8"= 1' -0"
    Plan # 1888-3
    "Terrace and Garden Walls." Item pieced together from 2 copies of drawing. This done at time of original installation in attic. Duplicate.
  - Mr & Mrs E.J. McDonnell, March 8, 1937 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 7)
    Windsor Place, Fox Chapel PA
    Scale 1/8" = 1'
    Plan No. 1886 – 1
    "Preliminary Sketch for Development of Garden and Area Around House." Garden plan shows a terraced garden room design, using formal stoned pathways and functional garden rooms close to the house, such as house terrace, lower terrace, overlook, and circular flower garden with axially placed pathways and benches. Circular driveway designed with service court. Informal woodland borders surround the perimeter of property. Average size drawing, 2' by 3'.
  - Garden of Mr. & Mrs. A.C. Sunstein, August 1937 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 7)
    1220 Bennington Ave.
    East End, Pittsburgh, PA
    Scale ¼" = 1'
    Plan #1904
    Preliminary rearrangement sketch. Garage court with arch arbor leading to Garden Lawn room. Low perennial edging with three flowering trees at each corner, with perennials surrounding the room behind low perennial edging. Bird bath centered in middle of lawn. Poplars lining backyard. Garden figures placed at corners of garden lawn. Drawing cut, missing top section, looks like layered underneath.
  - Mr. and Mrs. Howard Scott, March 1937 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 7)
    Woodside Rd.
    Forrest Hills, PA
    Elevation of garden property including play area and laundry yard, pool, flowerbeds.
  - Mr. and Mrs. Thomas Garman, October 1936 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 7)
    Planting plan
    Front of property
    Virginia Manor, Mount Lebanon
    Elevation drawings of gardens and full planting list.
  - Rose, Gretchen Elizabeth, October 1937 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 8)
    14th Ward, Pittsburgh, PA
    McBride Surveying & Engineering Company
    Commonwealth building Annex, Pittsburgh, PA
    By JR Fulton
    N.B. 182P115-117
    Plan of property in 14th Ward, Pittsburgh, surveyed for Gretchen Elizabeth Rose, Oct. 1937. Property plan for Rose. Adjoining properties include Sara N. Benedum and lot #12 & 13 for Christine Miller Clemson & Richard E.Clemson. Property off Highmont Rd. cul de sac.
  - Rose, Miss Gretchen Elizabeth, January 10, 1938; January 25, 1938 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 8)
    Highmont Plan, Pittsburgh PA
    Janssen & Cocken Registered Architects
    Drawing # 1
    Scale 1/8" = I'
    Residence of Rose. Plan shows footer of house, elevations, and contour lines. Standard size drawing, slightly torn in places.
  - Rose, Mrs. Gretchen Elizabeth, January 1, 1938 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 8)
    Highmont Plan, Pittsburgh, PA
    Jannsen &. Cocken, Registered Architects
    Commission # 831, Drawing # 7
    First floor plan of house, including stone walk and terrace. Drawing cut in half and refit. Torn in several places. Title block and drawing readable. Large size drawing.
  - Mrs. W J. Charles, November 1937 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 8)
    350 Midway Road, Mr. Lebanon, PA
    Scale ½"= 1'-0"
    No 1869-2
    "Construction Details for Rustic Shelter." Front elevation, floor plan of shelter. Describes how bark is to be stripped and how material is to be creosoted. Detail of seat support and section drawing showing stone paving and brick paving. Standard drawing, intact.
  - Mr. & Mrs. M. D. Bachrach, September 1938 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 8)
    Weller Road, Allegheny county, PA
    Plan #1929-1
    Planting plan. Small drawing, 1' x 2.5'. Section cut out of top. Planting plan surrounding a stone paved terrace and semicircular lawn area adjacent to an upper porch. A low stone wall and steps separate the terrace and porch. Plant material list is partially shown on plan, with part cut out. Deciduous trees, evergreen trees, and shrubs used.
  - Wright, Mr. and Mrs. Pearce, July 29, 1948 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 9)
    Sewickley Heights, Allegheny County, PA
    J. Phillips Davis, Architect
    Grogan Building, Pittsburgh, PA
    Size 38" x 19"
    Commission number 2203
    "Residence and Garage for Mr. & Mrs. Pearce Wright." Grading and plot plan. Shows original and finished grading. House on Stondale Road. Two corners of drawing cut off (part of title block).
  - Wright, Mr. & Mrs. H. Pearce, July 24, 1948 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 9)
    Sewickley Heights
    J. Phillip Davis, Architect
    Commission # 2203
    Sheet 1 of 8 drawings. Residence & garage: Plan of basement and foundations. Schedule of finishes. Large, intact drawing.
  - Wright, Mr. & Mrs H. Pearce, July 29, 1948 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 9)
    Arch. J. Phillips Davis, Architect
    Grogan Building
    Commission #2203
    Sheet 2 of 8 sheets. Residence & garage. Plan of first floor. Elevation of library book cases, cabinetry, and kitchen. Part of group of drawings. Large drawing.
  - Wright, Mr. & Mrs H. Pearce, July 29, 1948 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 9)
    J. Phillips Davis
    Sheet 6 of 8 sheets. Residence & Garage-side. (East) Elevation and (West) Elevation.
  - David Coslov, February 11, 1949 (Map-case 6, Drawer 6, Folder 9)
    Harry Lefkowitz, Architect
    Job # 3954